An Nguyen



an.nguyen@jhu.edu \(\cup-1\) 660-234-4266 in \(\link\) linkedin.com/in/an-d-nguyen/ \(\cap\) https://annguyen0212.github.io

2020 - 2021

Spring 2020

2013 - 2017

2016

2015

2013

SUMMARY

Cognitive scientist with with a focus on human perception and cognitive processes. 5 years of experience in experimental designs and data analysis/visualization. Familiar with NLP/NLU tasks and machine learning techniques, and experienced with many types of data: behavioral, eye-tracking, neuro-imaging, language analysis etc. Strong background in formal linguistics and experienced in building language models.

SKILLS	
Programming Skills: Python, R, JavaScript Languages: Vietnamese (native), English (fluent)	
EDUCATION	
Johns Hopkins University	
Ph.D. in Cognitive Science	2019 – present
M.A. in Cognitive Science	2018 - 2019
Truman State University	
B.S. in Psychology and Cognitive Science, Minor in Statistical Methods. Valedictorian.	2013 - 2017
RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE	
Graduate Researcher, LANGUAGE ACQUISITION LAB, JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY - First project: Investigated language acquisition using corpus data and computational linguistics - Second project: Tested syntax theories using behavioral experiments and corpus analysis - Third project: Created a Bayesian model of language acquisition in R and Python (PyMC3)	2018 – present
 Lab Manager, Language Acquisition and Brain Lab, University of Delaware Conducted research on perception and learning using behavioral, eye-tracking and neuro-imaging techniques. Supervised 3 research assistants. Managed the lab's database and workflow Lead data analyst and programmer for the lab's computer-based experiments. Lead web developer for the online platform with multiple interactive tasks to collect behavioral data. 	2017 – 2018
 Statistical Consultant, CENTER FOR APPLIED STATISTICS & EVALUATION Led a team of 3. Handled data analysis for several research projects and faculty grants Designed surveys and experiments, led focus groups, and generated statistical reports 	2015 – 2017
Research Assistant, EEG LAB, TRUMAN STATE UNIVERSITY - Conducted research on human perceptual processes (audio-visual integration) activity using EEG	2016 – 2017
APA Summer Undergraduate Research Scholar, Texas A&M University - Conducted research on the aging brain using meta-analysis, neuroimaging and brain stimulation	Summer 2016
Academic Trainer, STEP SCHOLARS PROGRAM - Tutored STEM subjects, including Computer Science, Mathematics, and Statistics Graded homework for advanced statistics courses.	2016 – 2017
AWARDS	

Science of Learning Fellowship for multidisciplinary approaches in studying cognition

Harold L. Hess and Ozella M. Hess Foundation Scholarship for academic excellence

Dorothy Pearson Foundation Scholarship for outstanding students in Statistics

President's Honorary Scholarship for outstanding incoming students

Graduate student travel award

President's List x 8 semesters

RELEVANT COURSEWORK

Computational Linguistics: Computational Linguistics; Computational Psycholinguistics; Human & Computer

Cognition; Intro to Human Language Technology

Computer Science: Object-oriented programming and design; Foundations of Neural Networks; Machine

Translation; Machine Learning – Deep Learning

Statistics: Statistical Computing; ANOVA; Linear Regression; Biostatistics; Advanced R

PUBLICATIONS

PAPERS

1. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. (2020). Covert movement in English probing wh-questions. In *Proceedings of Linguistic Society of America 2020 Annual Meeting*. 5(1). 180-186.

2. Bernard, JA, **Nguyen, A**, Hausman, HK, et al. (2020). Shaky scaffolding: Age differences in cerebellar activation revealed through activation likelihood estimation meta-analysis. *Human Brain Mapping*. 2020, 1–27.

TALKS

- 1. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. (2020). Testing syntactic simplicity: wh-in-situ vs. fronted wh-questions in L1 acquisition. Talk at *Many Paths to Language Max Planck Institute Conference*, Nijmegen, The Netherlands. Acceptance rate: **23.5%**
- 2. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. (2020). The acquisition of English wh-in-situ. Talk at the *Linguistic Society of America 2021 Annual Meeting*, San Francisco, CA. Acceptance rate: **35.2%**.
- 3. **Nguyen, A.** (2020). The acquisition of English wh-in-situ. *Brown Bag talk at the Cognitive Science Department, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD.*
- 4. **Nguyen, A.**, & Kozloff, V. (2017). Statistical learning and language. Talk at *the Experimental Group Meeting at the Department of Linguistics and Cognitive Science*, University of Delaware, Newark, DE.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

- 1. **Nguyen, A.,** Howe, W., & Legendre, G. (2020). English-speaking children's acquisition of wh-in-situ. Poster at *Generative Approaches to Language Acquisition North America* 6. Reykjavík, Iceland. Acceptance rate: **45%**
- 2. Weng, Y.L, **Nguyen, A.,** Ryskin, R., & Qi, Z. (2020). Prediction and sentence ambiguity resolution: A simultaneous eye-tracking and EEG study. Poster at *33rd Annual CUNY Human Sentence Processing Conference*, Amherst, MA.
- 3. Schneider, J., Arnon, I., **Nguyen, A.**, Medez, K., & Qi, Z. (2019). Does prior language experience hinder statistical learning? Poster presented at *Boston University Conference on Language Development*, Boston, MA.
- 4. Schneider, J., Weng, Y., Kozloff, V., **Nguyen, A.**, & Qi, Z. (2019). Neural sensitivity to speech distribution information underlise statistical learning. Poster presented at *Neurobiology of Language*, Helsinki, Finland.
- 5. Qi, Z., **Nguyen**, **A.**, Ozernov-Palchik, O., Beach, S., May, S., Arciuli, J., & Gabrieli, J.D.E. (2018). Statistical learning in reading development and reading impairment. Poster presented at *Boston University Conference on Language Development*, Boston, MA.
- 6. **Nguyen, A.**, Sanchez Araujo, Y., Georgan, W., Arciuli, J., & Qi, Z. (2018). Re-examine the reliability of statistical learning tasks across domains and modalities. Poster presented at *Psychonomic Society Annual Meeting*, New Orleans, LA.
- 7. Kozloff, V., **Nguyen, A.**, Arciuli, J., & Qi, Z. (2018). Statistical learning in a noisy environment is associated with vocabulary. Poster presented at *Boston University Conference on Language Development*, Boston, MA.
- 8. Mendez, K., **Nguyen, A.**, Kozloff, V., & Qi, Z. (2018). The role of native language in statistical learning success. Poster presented at *University of Delaware's ninth annual Undergraduate Research and Service Scholar Celebratory Symposium*, Newark, DE.

MANUSCRIPTS UNDER REVIEW

- 1. Schneider, J., Arnon, I., **Nguyen, A.**, Mendez, K., & Qi, Z. *The relationship between statistical learning and prior language experience*.
- 2. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. Distinguishing among in-situ wh questions in English: echo versus probing questions.
- 3. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. The acquisition of wh-questions: Beyond structural economy and input frequency.